<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/prototyping/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-04-04T01:21:45+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/prototyping/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">Lahiru Maramba | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Engineering &amp; Design Portfolio of Lahiru Maramba</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Cadence</title>
      <link href="/cadence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cadence" />
      <published>2019-03-12T10:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-12T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/cadence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/cadence">&lt;p&gt;Your body is the controller! Cadence is a rhythm game in which players tap along to the beats of a song on their thighs, and where certain beats are captured by high­ five-ing their teammate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/cd/cadence_hero.png#full&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;project-intro&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Timeline:&lt;/strong&gt; Fall 2016&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Course:&lt;/strong&gt; Game Design @ Queen’s University, Kingston, Canada&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Interaction Design, UI/UX, Prototyping&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Technologies:&lt;/strong&gt; C#, C++, Unity, Arduino&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-all-about-the-rhythm&quot;&gt;It’s All About The Rhythm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rhythm games require users to complete actions that correspond to the rhythm of the song that is being played. In recent years, rhythm games have grown rapidly in popularity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I find myself tapping on my thighs to the beat when I listen to music. I pitched this interaction idea to the team and we decided to design a game around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When I listen to music sometimes I start tapping along to the beat. Maybe we should make a game out of it!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular rhythm games like Rock Band require users to play with external peripherals that are in the shape of instruments or to make physical foot­ stepping movements like in the case of Dance Dance Revolution. However, these games do not take advantage of one of the most intuitive actions when listening to music: &lt;strong&gt;tapping along to the beat&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the current rhythm games aforementioned do not facilitate physical cooperation between players. They allow users to play multiple instruments at the same time, but they do not have a physically interactive teamwork component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-role&quot;&gt;My Role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was part of the Pitch Team and was responsible for the experience strategy and design of the gameplay. I was involved in the game interface and interaction design. I led the hardware design tasks, producing the wearable sensors that were robust and comfortable to wear and be used by the game players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-challenge&quot;&gt;The Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the ideation process we faced three interesting technological problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enabling players to use their bodies to communicate with the game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enabling players’ physical interactions to be communicated to the game in order to capture cooperative play&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyzing the audio of songs in order to automatically generate notes for gameplay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-solution&quot;&gt;Our Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve the first two problems we created a distributed system made up of micro-controllers and sensors to detect input from users’ bodies (both knee tapping and high­ five-ing), and transferring that input to Unity game engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third problem was solved by creating a beat detection algorithm that imitates the ways in which humans perceive beats in music. This was used to analyze songs and generate beats for gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our game includes a novel control scheme that requires the use of a number of external peripherals in order to enable players to utilize their body as the game “controller”. The players attach two wired square colour coded sensors (Piezo Sensors) on each leg using straps, and put on a wristband which is connected to the control box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-design-process&quot;&gt;The Design Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We used the feedback from our play-testers constantly throughout the project to guide design decisions, priorities, and create empathy amongst the users and our team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we created mock sensors with paper and cardboard and asked users to wear them pretending that they are real functional sensors. Then we presented them with our initial single player user interface and observed how users interact with the sensors and the game while making qualitative observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/cd/cadence_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/cd/cadence_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These early prototype evaluations helped us refine the initial design of the game before starting any development work. We conducted play testing sessions at each milestone to gather user feedback as we made improvements to the gameplay and game hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-evolution-of-the-game-interface&quot;&gt;The Evolution Of The Game Interface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created a two player layout that looks like two single player schemes stacked on top of each other. Play-testers did not have issues with this design, but what they did not find intuitive was the way in which cooperative notes were displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Collaborative Notes made the screen appear crowded and overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We initially had a yellow note in the middle of the screen, in between the two players individual gameplays. Notes that were to be played collaboratively would move across the middle of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/cd/cadence_04.png&quot; alt=&quot;The initial two player user interface looked like two single player schemes stacked on top of each other (where player 1 is on top and player 2 is on the bottom).&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The initial two player user interface looked like two single player schemes stacked on top of each other (where player 1 is on top and player 2 is on the bottom).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received informative feedback from users, and found that these collaborative notes made the screen appear crowded and overwhelming. Moreover, a common source of feedback was that the notes were just outside the player’s vertical peripheral vision (too high or too low) causing users to often not notice them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Collaborative Notes were just outside the player’s vertical peripheral vision, causing users to often not notice them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided that a shared note was not a feasible idea, and went forward with a different approach: When a note is to be played cooperatively, four hollow notes are generated from each of the player’s notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/cd/cadence_05.png&quot; alt=&quot;Iteration to the user interface with four hollow notes for collaborative play.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Iteration to the user interface with four hollow notes for collaborative play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We went forward with a different approach: When a note is to be played cooperatively, four hollow notes are generated from each of the player’s notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach to use four hollow notes for collaborative notes was received very positively by users. Four out of six users said that upon first seeing the set of four notes appear, they felt overwhelmed, but that they quickly adjusted to it. The other two users did not feel overwhelmed at any point. When asked if the new interface was confusing, all six users said no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/cd/cadence_06_final_ui.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final user interface with visual feedback representing the maximum combo multiplier.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Final user interface with visual feedback representing the maximum combo multiplier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People who are really serious about software should make their own hardware.” – Alan Kay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection--takeaways&quot;&gt;Reflection &amp;amp; Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing a novel gameplay and building a hardware interface to show its potential was a challenge. As a team, by coordinating our work between software, hardware interface, and game design, we overcame these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cadence encouraged physical interactions in collaborative gameplay between players. For similar future projects, I would further explore various aspects of collaborative gameplay and other ways of collaboration without physical interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3L74POQHuPo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>ghost</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="UX" />
      
        <category term="IxD" />
      
        <category term="Prototyping" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Your body is the controller! Cadence is a rhythm game in which players tap along to the beats of a song on their thighs, and where certain beats are captured by high­ five-ing their teammate.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Prototyping The Future of Smart Glasses</title>
      <link href="/prototyping" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prototyping The Future of Smart Glasses" />
      <published>2018-04-10T10:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-04-10T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/prototyping</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/prototyping">&lt;p&gt;Prototypes and early features built for Focals Smart Glasses at North Inc. Including Amazon Alexa integration, Speech to Text, and Screenshot Share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/frd/north_pty_cover.jpg#full&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;project-intro&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Timeline:&lt;/strong&gt; Winter 2017 to Present&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Organization&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bynorth.com/&quot; target=&quot;external&quot;&gt;North Inc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Team:&lt;/strong&gt; Software Prototyping&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Prototyping, Mobile Engineering, Interaction Design, UI/UX&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Technologies:&lt;/strong&gt; C++, Qt, C, Swift, Kotlin, Java, iOS, Android, React&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;wrap&quot;&gt;I have worked on a number of prototypes and early concepts for smart-glasses at North. Due to confidentiality, some of the work cannot be published. Below are some examples of my work at North that are now available in the final product.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;screenshot-share&quot;&gt;Screenshot Share&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feature allows users to share what they see on Focals with their contacts or on their social media networks. Users can add a personal touch and snap a photo with their smartphone camera as a screenshot background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was no quick and easy way for users to share what they are seeing on their glasses. We assumed that providing a quick and easy way to share screenshots would be valuable for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows users to share their excitement about product use cases, which is fun for the user and beneficial for our marketing efforts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows users to better communicate frustrations over product features that fail to live up to expectations so that we can improve the product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-goals&quot;&gt;Our Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow the user to press a button in Focals Companion mobile app to take a screenshot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow the user to select from multiple background images to make the screenshot more interesting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the final composition sharable directly from the mobile app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Limited ability to overload existing input methods to ensure fast and easy screenshot captures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating an appealing screenshot with a background image&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overlay a screenshot on any background such that the screenshot is clearly legible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/frd/user_flow_ss.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;initial-user-feedback&quot;&gt;Initial User Feedback&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conduced multiple demos for selected groups of internal users and gathered their feedback on the first iteration (a low-fidelity prototype) of the feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All participants preferred the ability to share what they see on Focals as a screenshot. Users mentioned that they would use screenshots to share the moments they experience on Focals. As a result of our findings this feature was graduated from a prototype to a feature in the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/frd/screenshot_share.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot Share feature is now available on Focals Companion App as part of the final product&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot Share feature is now available on Focals Companion App as part of the final product&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alexa&quot;&gt;Alexa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was part of the design and implementation team of the very first integration of Alexa on Focals smart-glasses. My role was to develop the initial interaction and software to connect Focals with Amazon Alexa services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/frd/alexa_pty.png&quot; alt=&quot;User flow and screens of the initial integration of Amazon Alexa on Focals.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;User flow and screens of the initial integration of Amazon Alexa on Focals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Focals come with Alexa built-in. Users can ask Alexa to play music, hear the news, see the weather, and control their smart home and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;speech-to-text&quot;&gt;Speech to Text&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I designed and implemented the very first version of Speech to Text feature on Focals smart-glasses. This initial implementation helped us test transcription accuracy and audio capture capabilities on Focals by conducting experiments and user studies. Speech to Text feature is now used in the final product as one of the main user input methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/frd/vtt.png&quot; alt=&quot;Speech to Text is used as a method of input on Focals when composing a message.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Speech to Text is used as a method of input on Focals when composing a message.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>ghost</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="Smart-glasses" />
      
        <category term="Mobile" />
      
        <category term="UX" />
      
        <category term="Prototyping" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Prototypes and early features built for Focals Smart Glasses at North Inc. Including Amazon Alexa integration, Speech to Text, and Screenshot Share.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">MagicWand</title>
      <link href="/magicwand" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MagicWand" />
      <published>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/magicwand</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/magicwand">&lt;p&gt;A handheld device with a fully cylindrical user interface that has a wide range of possible applications, including the use of as a game controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/mw/magic_wand_a.jpg#full&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;project-intro&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Timeline:&lt;/strong&gt; Winter 2016&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Research conducted at the Human Media Lab, Queen’s University&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Product Design, Interaction Design, Prototyping, Research &amp;amp; Evaluation&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Technologies:&lt;/strong&gt; C#, C++, Java, Unity, Arduino, Android&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;affordances-of-digital-devices&quot;&gt;Affordances Of Digital Devices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern smartphones with traditional flat screens offer poor affordances for gestural interactions. The flat form factor prevents a comfortable grip hindering wrist movements. Display area of flat devices can only be viewed from one side, and the visibility reduces when the device is rotated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-challenge&quot;&gt;The Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How might we create a new display form factor that will offer physical affordances for actions that are quite different from those of a traditional flat form factor of a smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-solution&quot;&gt;Our Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cylindrical device with a cylindrical display form factor that allows users to perform natural gestures and to explore the display area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interaction design was done based on how people handle day-to-day objects. The cylindrical form factor provides a comfortable grip when performing gestural interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success measures of the product revolve around how quickly a user can guess and performs an interaction based on the affordances provided by the cylindrical form factor and the visuals on the display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bring our product into fruition, we first had to empathize and understand how humans associate with affordances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started by looking for inspirations from Don Norman’s work on affordances &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Book&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Book&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We learned that affordances are generated by matching the fit of the body under action to the physical shape of an object. For example, a vertical door handle affords pulling, whereas a horizontal flat bar affords pushing to open &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Doors&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Doors&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-wrist-dont-lie&quot;&gt;Your Wrist Don’t Lie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ideation-process&quot;&gt;Ideation Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following our primary research, I then moved onto defining design parameters for gestural input devices. In the design process of MagicWand, I considered the following design parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cylindrical Shape and Ergonomic Tool Fit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimal Diameter and Length Tradeoff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conformability of the FOLEDs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conforming with Prior Gestural Game Controller Designs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unconstrained Motion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimal Design Space for Wrist Gestures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We envisioned MagicWand as an extension of the user’s wrist, supporting the maximum number of degrees of freedom provided by its joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/mw/wristmovements.png&quot; alt=&quot;The wrist is capable of three sets of distinct movements: flexion and extension, radial deviation and ulnar deviation, pronation and supination.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The wrist is capable of three sets of distinct movements: flexion and extension, radial deviation and ulnar deviation, pronation and supination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We based our initial set of gestures for MagicWand on the above capabilities of the wrist: providing gestures for &lt;strong&gt;rotation&lt;/strong&gt; (pronation/supination), &lt;strong&gt;tilt&lt;/strong&gt; (flexion/extension), as well as &lt;strong&gt;pointing&lt;/strong&gt; (deviation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Motion gesture design was also inspired by everyday object handling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motion gesture design was also inspired by everyday object handling. For example, actions such as turning a key to unlock a door, or turning a door knob to open a door, involve rotation through pronation/supination of the wrist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/mw/magicw_sketches.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MagicWand Design Sketches&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When handling cylindrical fluid containers such as bottles, the object is naturally tilted through flexion extension of the wrist to drink from or pour liquid out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pointing with a cylindrical object such as a remote control, laser pointer, or stick involves radial and ulnar deviations of the wrist. Deviations of the wrist becomes a motion gesture when cutting or slashing using tools such as knives and swords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were similarly inspired by the swirl motion used when stirring food with a kitchen utensil such as a spoon, which involves a combination of deviation and flexion/extension actions by the wrist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-physical-product&quot;&gt;The Physical Product&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MagicWand is a cylindrical display device consisting of two 5.5” Flexible Organic Light-Emitting Diode (FOLED) screens wrapped around a 3D printed body. MagicWand features a smartphone running the Android operating system. Gesture recognition allows the use of the wand movements as a form of input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/mw/magicwand_explodedView_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Physical Prototype Design. (1) 3D printed body, (2) Android boards, (3) Flexible OLED Displays, (4) Cooling fan.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Physical Prototype Design. (1) 3D printed body, (2) Android boards, (3) Flexible OLED Displays, (4) Cooling fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fantasy-game-application&quot;&gt;Fantasy Game Application&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To highlight some of MagicWand’s capabilities, we developed a first-person fantasy adventure game for aspiring wizards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… — a candle, a wand, a key, a whirlwind, a sword, a magic potion, and a spoon — …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game requires the player to use several tools that fit a cylindrical form factor — a &lt;strong&gt;candle&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;wand&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;key&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;whirlwind&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;magic potion&lt;/strong&gt;, and a &lt;strong&gt;spoon&lt;/strong&gt; — to interact with characters that fit a cylindrical form. The game’s goal is to collect all the characters and transport them from the wand display to a virtual magical island on a large external display, through the application of gestures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/mw/magicwand_gameplay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A player interacting with MagicWand, (Top) unlocking a dungeon door using a virtual Key, (Bottom) destroying a spider web that obstructs the player’s path with a Sword.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A player interacting with MagicWand, (Top) unlocking a dungeon door using a virtual Key, (Bottom) destroying a spider web that obstructs the player’s path with a Sword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/mw/magicwand_compare.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; (Top) Flat displays have a display area that can only be viewed from one side, and the visibility is reduced when the device is rotated. (Bottom) When the wand is rotated, the graphics circumnavigate according to IMU data giving the illusion of motion parallax.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; (Top) Flat displays have a display area that can only be viewed from one side, and the visibility is reduced when the device is rotated. (Bottom) When the wand is rotated, the graphics circumnavigate according to IMU data giving the illusion of motion parallax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection--takeaways&quot;&gt;Reflection &amp;amp; Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ambition for this project was exciting but also daunting. Building a completely new hardware device and then software applications that runs on it was a huge challenge. During the process I broke more than 20 flexible OLED screens. However, with the help of my team at the end I was able to create a novel display device and built a game application to showcase its potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MagicWand was designed with specific design goals and under particular technical constraints. Although the empirical findings support the design rationale, many of the details in the experimental results pertain only to the specific hardware capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing interactions with MagicWand we relied solely on gesture control. All tasks were triggered only using motion gestures, which can be more difficult to discover than touch interactions. Based on these limitations, future work needs to be conducted to explore the interactions with both touch input and gestures combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eFHyRWFf2Qs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Book&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/840.The_Design_of_Everyday_Things&quot;&gt;Design of Everyday Things&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Book&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Doors&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yY96hTb8WgI&quot;&gt;Norman Doors&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Doors&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>ghost</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="UX" />
      
        <category term="IxD" />
      
        <category term="Prototyping" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A handheld device with a fully cylindrical user interface that has a wide range of possible applications, including the use of as a game controller.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
